Raymond, Eleanor. The Eleanor Raymond Collection: An Inventory.
Eleanor Raymond Collection.
1927-1975
Special Collections, Frances Loeb Library, Graduate School of Design, Harvard University
DES.1986.0001.009331040
Raymond, Eleanor.
10 linear feet
Extent is approximate
Project files, drawings, correspondence, photographs and personal papers drawn from the professional and personal files of architect Eleanor Raymond.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eleanor Raymond, 1986.
Conditions on Use and Access
Contact Special Collection Department, Frances Loeb Library, Harvard Design School.
Biography
Eleanor Raymond was born in 1888 in Cambridge, MA, and following her graduation from Wellesley College, enrolled in the Cambridge School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture (whose faculty was largely drawn from the faculty of Harvard’s School of Architecture). Upon her graduation in 1919, Raymond joined Henry Atherton Frost: the beginning of a professional career that was to span some sixty years of practice. Raymond’s prime interest was in residential housing: she designed one of the first International Style houses in the United States in 1931, and she was deeply interested in innovative materials and building systems (designing a Plywood House in 1940 and in 1948, the “Sun House,” one of the first successful solar-heated buildings in the Northeast). Eleanor Raymond was elected a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects in 1961.
The Eleanor Raymond Collection includes documentation of some 300 architectural projects, ranging from drawings to related correspondence, as well as project photographs, personal papers, snapshots, and memorabilia. Also included are diaries kept by architectural journalist and writer Ethel Power, Raymond’s long-time companion and professional colleague.
The collection has been arranged into four series. Series A: Project Files Related to Eleanor Raymond’s Professional Practice. Series B: Published and Unpublished Materials Related to Eleanor Raymond’s Professional Practice. Series C: Photographs, Other Graphic Material and Memorabilia Related to Eleanor Raymond’s Professional Practice. Series D: Manuscript and Other Materials Related to Eleanor Raymond’s Personal Life.
- Series A / Project Files, A000
  - Project Files: Goldthwaite Project, / Date(s): 1927; : A275
    Content: Flat file contains 1 black and white exterior photograph of entrance; 13-1/2" x 14-1/2", mounted.
  - Project Files: Barnes House Renovation, / Date(s): 1929; : A2912
    Note: An extensive residential renovation.
    Content: Box #1 contains House Beautiful (August 1933) and Architectural Record (October 1934) articles.
    Content: Flat file contains 3 black and white photographs of exterior and interior; 13" x 17" and 19-1/2" x 23-1/2", unmounted. One has label of 1938 Boston Architectural Society Exhibit pinned to it.
    Published in: Published in D. Cole's Eleanor Raymond, architect; Architectural Record 76 (October 1834), "Remodeled House of Frank Barnes, Haverhill, Massachusetts", 300-302; House Beautiful August 1933, 41-44; and House Beautiful 1932.
  - Project Files: Residence, / Date(s): 1930; : A304
    Note: See record #4903.
  - Project Files: Peabody Pig House, / Date(s): 1948; : A3311
    Note: Items in Box #1 include specifications and painting schedule.
  - Project Files: Peabody Sculpture Studio, / Date(s): 1933; : A333
    Note: Project files related to Amelia Peabody's Sculpture Studio, Mill Farm, Dover, MA. Amelia ("Amy") Peabody was a longtime friend and continuing client who sponsored some of E. Raymond's most creative work.
    Content: Box #1 contains House Beautiful (August 1934), Architectural Forum (May 1938) and Architectural Forum (July 1937) articles.
    Content: Flat file contains 4 b&w interior and exterior photographs; 2 mounted 15" x 20", 1 mounted 18" x 23" and 1 mounted 18" x 23". Label: Office of Eleanor Raymond, 126 Newbury Street, Boston, MA. 3 negatives, 8" x 10" in envelope.
    Published in: Published in Architectural Forum, May 1938; D. Cole; Architectural Forum, 67 (July 1937), "Sculptor's Studio, Dover, Massachusetts: E. Raymond, Architect", 36-37; House Beautiful, August, 1934, 32-32 & 66.
  - Project Files: Peabody Farm Buildings, / Date(s): 1934; : A343
    Note: Project files related to Peabody Projects, Mill Farm, Dover, MA. These are various farm buildings.
    Content: Box #1 contains specifications, 3" x 5" black and white photographs of Peabody farm buildings and House Beautiful article of December 1935.
    Content: Flat file contains 1 black and white exterior photograph by George H. Davis Studio, Boston, MA; 7-1/2" x 9-1/2", mounted on card stock. Edges broken.
    Published in: Published in D. Cole.
  - Project Files: Sugarman House, / Date(s): 1935; : A3511
    Note: Project files related to Sugarman Residence, Brookline, MA.
    Content: Box #1 contains specifications.
  - Project Files: Peabody Projects, / Date(s): 1935-1961; : A3515
    Note: Project files related to Peabody Projects, Mill Farm, Dover, MA. and 120 Commonwealth Ave., Boston, MA. Various alterations to residence, barn and town house. Shop drawings from 1961. Goes with #359.
  - Project Files: Farnsworth Projects, / Date(s): 1935-1961; : A3516
    Note: Project files related to additions, alterations and construction of small domestic buildings at the property of Marion B. Farnsworth, Ashby, MA. E. Raymond did several projects for Miss Farnsworth around this time.
  - Project Files: Elliott House, / Date(s): 1935-1936; : A3517
    Note: Project files related to Elliott House.
  - Project Files: Frost House, / Date(s): 1935; : A3518
    Note: Project files related to the Frost House, Cambridge, MA.
    Note: This is a very visible house on Longfellow Park in Cambridge, MA.
    Content: Box #1 contains specifications, outline specifications and House Beautiful Building Manual article, Spring 1940, 29.
  - Project Files: Pinney House, / Date(s): 1936; : A3522
    Note: Project file related to the Pinney House.
  - Project Files: Farnsworth House Renovation, / Date(s): 1935; : A353
    Note: Project files related to Farnsworth House Renovation, Exmoor Farm, Boston Post Road, Weston, MA. Well-documented project. E. Raymond did several other projects for Miss Farnsworth.
  - Project Files: Peabody Greenhouse, / Date(s): 1935; : A359
    Note: Project files related to Peabody Greenhouse, Mill Farm, Dover, MA. with #3515.
  - Project Files: Smith House Addition, / Date(s): 1936; : A3610
    Note: Smith Residence Addition, 59 Central Street, Andover, MA. Reference to "Dodge House" Project #358, not found. Mary Byers Smith a friend and continuing client of E. Raymond in Massachusetts and in Maine.
  - Project Files: Smith House Addition, / Date(s): 1936; : A3611
    Note: Project files related to Wigglesworth House, Milton, MA.
    Note: Contains measured drawings of existing residence. Extensive interior detailing.
  - Project Files: Bradley House (for Amelia Peabody), / Date(s): 1936; : A364
    Note: Bradley House for Amelia Peabody, Dover, MA. A residence with office; sketches for later alterations; combination of sidings. Additional sketches mis-filed in #365. Peabody a friend and repeating client.
  - Project Files: Miller House, / Date(s): 1936; : A365
    Note: Contains print of Olmsted grading plan for Hornblower sub-division. Simple lines, window treatment. Mis-filed sketches for Bradley House #364. Near E. Raymond's house for Rachel Raymond (sister), 1930.
    Published in: Published in Architectural Forum, 72 (February 1940), "Belmont House for T. T. Miller", 112-113; and in D. Cole,
  - Project Files: Ballantine House Addition, / Date(s): 1937; : A3715
    Note: Project files related to Ballantine House, Vineyard Haven, MA. Contains measured drawings of existing house and 1939 Garden Plan.
  - Project Files: Pillsbury House, / Date(s): 1937; : A3717
    Note: Project files related to Pillsbury House, Duxbury, MA.
    Note: Includes shop drawings of aluminum light fixtures by Litecontrol Corp. Built-in and other furniture drawings.
    Note: Sarah Pillsbury, Assistant Architect.
    Published in: Published in Architectural Forum, 75 (December 1941), "Duxbury House: E. Raymond Pillsbury, Architects", 402-403.
  - Project Files: Farnsworth Projects, / Date(s): 1937-1941; : A372
    Note: Marion B. Farnsworth, Exmoor Farm, Boston Post Road, Weston, MA.
    Note: This is animal housing and residential designs. One later drawing from 1964. Also includes #373, #374.
  - Project Files: Olmsted House, / Date(s): 1937; : A376
    Note: Project files related to Olmsted House, 35 Glencoe Road, Chestnut Hill, MA. First floor plan missing; furniture sketches from 1944.
    Note: Mis-filed plot plan Dickerson, Maine?
    Published in: Cited by D. Cole
  - Project Files: Bartel House, / Date(s): 1937; : A377
    Note: Project files related to William P. Bartel House, Gleason Road, Wayland, MA. Includes structural drawings by A.O. Wilson. Contractor: Bernard Eckberg. Extensive detailing.
  - Project Files: Farnsworth Cabin, / Date(s): 1937; : A378
    Note: Project files related to Farnsworth Cabin, Weston, MA. This is an addition to thatch cabin and dog house. E. Raymond did several projects for Farnsworth in these years.
  - Project Files: Old Flag Tavern Conversion, / Date(s): 1938; : A384
    Note: Project files related to Marion B. Farnsworth's project for converting Old Flagg Tavern to a residence.
  - Project Files: Hunt House, / Date(s): 1938-1944; : A386
    Note: Hunt House, Weston, MA. Includes sketches for new west wing (1954). Wile involved in contract. Marion B. Farnsworth for Mrs. Hunt? Farnsworth and Wile friends of E. Raymond and clients.
    Published in: Published in Architectural Forum, 79 (November 1943), "House in Weston, Massachusetts", 82-83.
  - Project Files: Gun Club Cottage Addition, / Date(s): 1938; : A387
    Note: Project file related to Gun Club Cottage addition. Also includes #389.
  - Project Files: Apple House Apartment (Renovation), / Date(s): 1938; : A389
    Note: Project files relate to Apple House Apartment renovation; fenestration.
  - Project Files: Peabody Garage Addition, / Date(s): 1939; : A392
    Note: Project files relating to Peabody Garage Addition, Mill Farm, Dover. MA. This is a garage addition to a dog kennel. Heating plan by General Heat.
  - Project Files: Farnsworth Projects, / Date(s): 1939; : A395
    Note: Project files related to Farnsworth Projects, Exmoor Farm, Dover, MA. Project consists of three residences, garage and stable. Influence of early Pennsylvania buildings. Grouped housing.
  - Project Files: Besse House, / Date(s): 1939; : A398
    Note: Project files related to Besse House, Vineyard Haven, MA. Blueprints of heating plan by General Heat and Appliance. Trade notes.
  - Project Files: Simplex Engineering Building, / Date(s): 1940; : A4013
    Note: Project files related to Simplex Engineering Building, corner of Newark Road and Adams Lane Falls Turnpike, Muskingum County, Ohio. Concrete block with steel sash windows and built-up roof. See #4014.
  - Project Files: Wile Shop, / Date(s): 1940; : A4014
    Note: Project files related to the Wile Shop. This is a concrete block building with flat roof; corner windows by Hope Steel Windows. Wile was a builder E. Raymond worked with repeatedly. Includes #4013 and #412 (sign sketch).
  - Project Files: Farnsworth Driver's House Shed, / Date(s): 1940; : A4017
    Note: Project files related to Farnsworth Driver's House Shed.
    Note: Sketches for conversion of Driver's House Shed into two apartments.
  - Project Files: Scott House, / Date(s): 1940; : A4018
    Note: Project files related to Scott House, Barrington, Rhode Island. Very nice hand-drawn sketches of traditional design.
  - Project Files: Peabody Plywood House, / Date(s): 1940-1941; : A404
    Note: Peabody Plywood House, Powisset Street, Dover, MA. Masonite and plywood construction; horizontal fenestration.
    Content: Box #2 contains 13 - 8" x 10" negatives and 9 - 8" x 10" black and white prints of the Plywood House.
    Content: Flat files contain 2 black and white photographs of interior and exterior; 11" x 14", unmounted.
  - Project Files: Ballantine Barn Renovation, / Date(s): 1940; : A407
    Note: Project files related to Ballantine Barn alteration, Vineyard Haven, MA.
    Note: Hand-drawn design sketches.
  - Project Files: Thayer House Renovation, / Date(s): 1941; : A412
    Note: Project files related to Thayer House (renovation). Sketches for H. E. Wile Builder sign mis-filed here. See #4014.
  - Project Files: Parker Plywood House, / Date(s): 1941, 1945-1946; : A416
    Note: Project files related to Parker Plywood House, 7 Ledgewood Road, Winchester, MA. Use of interior and exterior plywood; extensive furnishing/fixture detailing. Parker family made plywood.
    Content: Flat file contains 42 black and white interior and exterior photographs by Haskell, Architectural Photographer, 21 Cedar Street, Marblehead, MA: 8" x 10", unmounted. Some stamped by Haskell, others possibly reprints.
    Content: Flat file contains rendering; pencil on board; 12" x 19". Labelled "Office of Eleanor Raymond Architect" and "Brodie (delimeator) 10.17.41".
    Published in: Published in D. Cole. Architectural Record, 103 (June 1948), "House in Winchester, Massachusetts: Views and Floor Plans", 103-105. Box #1 contains Architectural Record article of June, 1948.
  - Project Files: Farnsworth Blue Gates Renovation, / Date(s): 1944; : A417
    Note: Project file related to renovation at Ashby, MA.
  - Project Files: Hammond Compound, / Date(s): 1941-1942; : A419
    Note: Hammond Compound, Dolliver's Neck, Gloucester, MA. Large and extensively detailed residential sets; four houses, barns, sheds, garages. Miss Hammond was a neighbor and friend of E. Raymond in Gloucester, MA.
    Content: Flat files contain 1 black and white photograph through gate to interior courtyard; 8" x 10-1/2", mounted.
  - Project Files: Smith House Addition, / Date(s): 1942-1946, 1955-1958; : A4210
    Note: Project files related to Smith House, Biddeford Pool, Maine. Concrete block; plywood furniture. Sketch for sun-heater installation sent to Maria Telkes, 1946.
  - Project Files: Power House Remodeling, / Date(s): 1942; : A424
    Note: Masonite porch sketch mis-filed here. See #4414, Masonite House.
  - Project Files: Ballantine House, / Date(s): 1943; : A4311
    Note: Project files related to Ballantine residence, Brewster, MA. Hand-drawn sketches.
  - Project Files: Power Ltd. House Addition, / Date(s): 1944; : A4410
    Note: Mis-filed drawing belonging in #453.
  - Project Files: Wile House, / Date(s): 1944-1946; : A4412
    Note: Project files related to Wile House, 141 Meadowbrook Road, Weston, MA.
    Note: Includes plywood furniture from 1948, 1949, 1953. Sketch for 1954 terrace, garden. Sketch for 1957 addition.
    Note: Some prints are stamped with photographers name on verso.
    Content: Flat files contain 41 black and white photographs by Haskell, 21 Cedar Street, Marblehead, MA; 23 exterior and 18 interior; 8" x 10", unmounted.
  - Project Files: Peabody "Herdsman" Project / Cottage, / Date(s): 1946; : A4414
    Note: Project files related to "Herdsman" cottage project. Plumbing and heating plan. Measured drawings of Peabody Masonite House mis-filed under #453. Porch details of Masonite House mis-filed under #424 (labelled #4414)
    Content: Flat file contains 2 black and white negatives; 8" x 10" in envelope.
    Content: Box #1 contains 21 - 8" x 10" black and white photographs and a few 8" x 10" negatives in envelope.
  - Project Files: Barnes House Renovation, / Date(s): 1944; : A442
    Note: Project files related to Barnes House, Haverhill, MA. Hand-drawn elevations.
  - Project Files: Buswell House Remodeling, / Date(s): 1944-1946; : A444
    Note: Project files related to Buswell House (Remodeling), Stillington Hall, Gloucester, MA. Includes small perspectives.
  - Project Files: Jackson House, / Date(s): 1944; : A446
    Note: Project files related to Jackson House. Includes #339. Anderson windows.
    Published in: Cited in Ethel Power's book The Smaller American House.
  - Project Files: Farnsworth Barn Renovation, / Date(s): 1944; : A447
    Note: Project files related to Farnsworth Barn (renovation). Barn apartment conversion.
  - Project Files: The Retreat, / Date(s): 1945; : A449
    Note: Filed following #4412.
  - Project Files: Williams House, / Date(s): 1947; : A4511
    Note: Project files related to Williams House, Nashawtuc Hill, Concord, MA.
    Note: Concrete block; fenestration. Sepia prints used for electric work. Hopes steel windows; built-ins. See #456 for mis-filed print.
    Content: Flat file contains 4 color photographs of exterior with handwritten note to "show to Doris Cole"; 3-1/2" x 5", unmounted.
  - Project Files: MacInnis Projects, / Date(s): 1945-1954; : A4512
    Note: Project files related to MacInnis residential projects. Includes new "garden house."
  - Project Files: Gloucester Red Cross, / Date(s): 1945; : A4514
    Note: Project files related to Gloucester Red Cross. Renovation of existing building for use by Red Cross. Use of sepia prints for electrical work.
  - Project Files: Barnes Townhouse Renovation, / Date(s): 1945; : A4517
    Note: Project files related to Barnes Townhouse renovation, 46 Chestnut Street, Boston, MA.
  - Project Files: SmithTownhouse Renovation, / Date(s): 1950, 1958-1959; : A4518
    Note: Project files related to Smith Townhouse Renovation, 89 Pinckney Street, Boston, MA. Stackpole survey (#4522) mis-filed here.
  - Project Files: Stackpole House Addition, / Date(s): 1945-1947; : A4522
    Note: Project files related to Stackpole House Addition, Biddeford Pool, Maine.
    Note: Mis-filed survey for #4518 filed here.
  - Project Files: Frost House Renovation, / Date(s): 1946; : A4528
    Note: Project file related to the Frost property, Manchester, MA.
  - Project Files: Power Ltd. Project, / Date(s): 1945; : A453
    Note: See #4410 and #4414 for mis-filed drawings.
  - Project Files: Douglas Kitchen Remodeling, / Date(s): 1946; : A4530
    Note: Project files related to Douglas Kitchen Remodeling. Drawings executed by drafter.
  - Project Files: Wood House Renovation, / Date(s): 1945; : A454
    Note: Project file related to Wood House. These are measured casework details.
  - Project Files: Crosby Townhouse Renovation, / Date(s): 1949; : A456
    Note: Project files related to Crosby Townhouse Renovation, 9 Louisburg Square, Boston, MA. Conversion into three apartments. Use of drawing on blueprint as design tool. Mis-filed drawings for #552.
  - Project Files: Anderson Townhouse Remodeling, / Date(s): 1945; : A458
    Note: Project files related to Anderson Townhouse remodeling, 47 Chestnut Street, Boston, MA. Built-ins.
  - Project Files: Fitzgibbon Renovations, / Date(s): 1946; : A4602
    Note: Project files related to Fitzgibbon residential renovations. Drawing file includes note from client and Polaroid pictures.
    Content: Correspondence file contains blueprint, sketches and survey.
  - Project Files: Anderson Renovations, / Date(s): 1946-1947; : A4605
    Note: Project file related to Anderson property.
  - Project Files: Power Interior Alterations, / Date(s): 1946; : A4610
    Note: Project files related to Power residential alterations, Acorn Street.
    Note: Design for living room alterations and built-in furniture.
  - Project Files: Brennan Garden Plan, / Date(s): 1946; : A4611
    Note: Project file of landscape plan.
  - Project Files: Power Webster House Alterations, / Date(s): 1946; : A4612
    Note: Project file related to Webster House, Cambridge, MA.
  - Project Files: Williams House Renovations, / Date(s): 1946-1947, 1949, 1952; : A4614
    Note: Project files related to Williams House Renovations, 11 Main Street, Rockport, MA. Blueprinted material drawn by B. Williams.
  - Project Files: Munn House Interior Renovations, / Date(s): 1946; : A4615
    Note: Project file.
  - Project Files: Shattuck House Interior Renovations, / Date(s): 1946; : A4616
  - Project Files: Morse House Renovations, / Date(s): 1946; : A4617
    Note: Project files related to Morse House Renovations. Includes good elevation drawings.
  - Project Files: G.I. House, / Date(s): 1946; : A4618
    Note: Project file related to prototype design.
  - Project Files: Doctor's Office, / Date(s): 1946; : A4620
    Note: Project file related to window design/renovation.
  - Project Files: Olmsted House Addition, / Date(s): 1946-1947; : A4621
  - Project Files: Dunsford House Renovations, / Date(s): 1946; : A4623
  - Project Files: Proposal for an Inn, / Date(s): 1947; : A4627
    Note: Project file for a proposed inn, to be located at Center Sandwich, NH.
  - Project Files: Blick Alteration Projects, / Date(s): 1946-1947; : A4629
    Note: Project files related to Blick Alterations Projects, Mussel Point, Gloucester, MA. Alterations to residence and barn. Use of Marlite and pre-fabricated cabinets.
  - Project Files: Peabody Barn Cottage Alteration, / Date(s): 1947; : A4702
    Note: Project file related to alterations to structure on the Peabody property, Dover, MA.
  - Project Files: Adams Barracks, / Date(s): 1947; : A4704
    Note: Project files related to Adams Barracks, Bailey Island, Maine. Plate glass and steel at Music House. Interior detailing; built-ins; casework. Modifications to house.
  - Project Files: Rust Garage, / Date(s): 1947; : A4708
    Note: Project files related to Rust Garage. Use of cinder block; flat roof.
    Note: Also labeled #4721.
  - Project Files: Proposed Inn, / Date(s): 1947; : A4710
    Note: Location of Proposed Inn not indicated.
  - Project Files: Peabody Kitchen Alteration, / Date(s): 1963; : A4711
    Note: Project file related to work undertaken at Peabody property, Boston, MA.
  - Project Files: Burrill House, / Date(s): 1947; : A4712
    Note: Project files related to Burrill House, Marmion Way, Rockport, MA. Semi-open plan. Glass slats at entrance.
    Published in: Published in D. Cole
  - Project Files: Mixter Barn Renovation, / Date(s): 1947; : A4714
    Note: Project file related to work at Mixter property, Wood's Hole, MA.
  - Project Files: Dickerson House, / Date(s): 1947-1949; : A4715
    Note: Project files related to Dickerson House, Hancock Point, Maine. Traditional; semi-open plan; built-in furnishings. See #376 for survey plan.
  - Project Files: Beebe Kitchen Alteration, / Date(s): 1947; : A4717
    Note: Location of property not indicated.
  - Project Files: Bass House Renovations, / Date(s): 1947; : A4719
    Note: Project file related to work underatken at Bass House, Peterboro, NH.
  - Project Files: Cram House Alterations, / Date(s): 1947; : A4720
  - Project Files: Peabody Sun-Heated House, / Date(s): 1948; : A4802
    Note: Project files related to Peabody Sun-Heated House, Powisset Street, Dover, MA. Solar design developed with Maria Telkes, MIT. Aluminum roof.
    Content: Flat file contains one black and white photograph of exterior by Life Magazine; 10-1/2" x 13-1/2", unmounted. One black and white negative, 8" x 10" in envelope.
    Content: Box #1 contains photograph and negative of E. Raymond and M. Telkes at Dover Solar House. It is located in file folder marked "Dwellings - Eleanor Raymond."
    Content: Correspondence files contain blueprints, blackline prints, sketches and shop drawings, as well as correspondence and notes concerning exhibits.
    Published in: Published in Architectural Record, 105 (March 1949), "Test House Heated only by Solar Heat", 136-137. Also published in D. Cole.
  - Project Files: Mason House, / Date(s): 1948, 1951, 1956, 1959; : A4805
    Note: Project file related to Mason House, "Twin Oaks", Simon Willard Road, Concord, MA. Large expanse of Thermopane glass.